你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎来到pwn学院的自动化漏洞挖掘模块
welcome to the Automated Vulnerability Discovery Module of pwn College
在本模块中，我们将学习如何自动识别漏洞
in this module we're going to look at how to automatically identify vulnerabilities
我们整个学期都在讨论漏洞
we've been talking about vulnerabilities throughout the entire semester
我们发现、理解、识别并利用了各种各样的漏洞
different types of vulnerabilities that you've examined understood identified in software and exploited
一直没试过自动化查找漏洞
never going to try to figure out how to automatically find these vulnerabilities
这并不容易
and it's not easy
我们为什么要关心自动化漏洞挖掘
so why do we care about automatically finding them
我们手动查找的好好地
you've done just fine finding them manually
但是如果你回想一下课程的开始
but if you think back to the beginning of the course
我们讨论过Phineas Fisher
we talked about Phineas Fisher
黑掉黑客团队的著名黑客
the hacker that famously brought down Hacking Team
使用找到的一个嵌入式设备上的0day漏洞
using an embedded device 0 day that they found
它是黑客团队暴露在互联网上的极少数设备之一
in one of the very few devices that Hacking Team had exposed to the internet
这些设备没有公开的漏洞
there was no publicly known vulnerability in these devices
但他表示我要黑进去
the Phineas Fisher just said I will get into that device
他们检查了设备固件
they looked at the device firmware
识别出了0day漏洞
identified a zero day
获取到入侵点
and gained entry
引发了连锁反应，基本上毁了HackingTeam公司
and started this chain reaction that basically destroyed Hacking Team as a company
原因是我们手动挖掘赶不上时代
the bottom line is we're not keeping up
这是一张历年CVE数量图表
this is a graph of the number of CVEs Common Vulnerability Enumeration
CVE编号是给安全研究人员的奖杯
a trophy that is given to security researchers
用于表彰安全研究员发现并上报漏洞
that identify and report security vulnerabilities over time and
可以清楚的看到CVE数量的大量上升
you can clearly see a gigantic increase in the number of CVEs granted
现在发现的CVE数量至少
where nowadays we are getting at least twice as many CVEs
是零几年的2倍
as we did in the height of the early 2000s
我们发现了很多漏洞
and we're finding a lot of bugs
但想问一下
but it's valid to ask
这是否意味着
does this mean that maybe there
我们找到了这么多bug
we're finding all the bugs
未知bug应该变少了吧
and there are fewer bugs out there
不幸的是，情况并非如此
unfortunately this doesn't seem to be the case
如果这张图叠上
if you overlay this graph
这张2006年至今的Linux代码行数图
on a graph of the lines of code in the Linux kernel over time from 2006 to the modern day
看起来很严峻
the picture looks grim
如果我们假设代码有一定的bug率
if we assume that code is buggy to some percentage
假设每n行包含一个bug
where every n lines contains a bug
这是个合理的假设
which is not an unreasonable Assumption
它不一定有科学依据支撑
it's not necessarily science backed
但也许我们能从一些数据中看出来
but probably there is data that we could look around for this
如果我们做这个假设
if we make this Assumption
那么我们可以清楚地发现
then we can clearly see
找到的bug数未达到应有的bug数
we are not finding as many bugs as we should be finding
鉴于软件增加的复杂性
given the increase in complexity in the software that we're working with
当然，你可能会说
of course you might say okay
Linux内核代码量可能增长的比其它软件快
but the Linux kernel maybe is growing faster than other software
但从另一方面来看
but on a whole different axis
如今现有的软件数量远超过
we have much much much more software nowadays
前几年的软件数
than we did even a couple years ago
数以百万计地增加的
the proliferation of millions and millions
像Javascript代码、框架、小辅助库等
of Javascript frameworks and little helper libraries and all of this insane stuff
Github的崛起
the rise of Github
现有的Github仓库数是三年前的两倍
we have twice as many Github repositories now as we did just three years ago
有很多代码可能被人们使用
it's a lot of code that is out there possibly being used by people
几乎可以肯定是有漏洞的
probably almost certainly vulnerable
所以我们需要一些自动化的方法来识别更多的漏洞
so we need some automated way of identifying more vulnerabilities
显然这不是新鲜事
obviously this isn't news
事实上，研究人员几十年来一直在思考这个问题
in fact researchers have been thinking about this for decades
不确定是不是从1949年起，总之很久之前
not quite back to 1949 but fairly far
1949年，艾伦·图灵，图灵机等概念的发明者
in 1949 Alan Turning whom you might know as the inventor of concepts such as the turning machine
他是计算机科学史上非常重要的人物
very important figure in computer science history
艾伦·图灵提出了一个算法
Alan Turning proposed an algorithm
它可以用来检查大型函数的正确性
that could be used to check a large routine a large function for correctness
这是艾伦·图灵所关心的是
now Alan Turning was concerned about
程序写得得当吗
is this program written properly
一个非常值得关注的问题是这个程序的安全性
a very concern is this program written securely
但是你可以这样说
but you can make the argument
很多团体也都这样认为
and various groups do make the argument that
如果说程序编写得当，它必须是安全的
if a program is written properly it will be secured
安全性应该是规范的一部分
that should be part of the proper specification
有趣的是
interestingly enough
艾伦·图灵谈到了检查程序
Alan Turning talks about checking programs
我第一次读这篇论文的时候
and the first time I read this paper
我觉得这家伙真是太超前了
i think wow this dude is so far ahead of his time
讲到了这个校验者检查这个，那个校验者检查那个
talking about the verifier does this the verifier does that
1949年，人们几乎不了解软件
people are barely thinking about software in 1949
他已经在考虑用软件验证其他软件
and he's already thinking about software validating other software
然后我读到一处
and then I got to a part in the paper
这里的表达方式让我突然意识到
where something was phrased in a way that I suddenly realized
艾伦·图灵说的校验者
oh Alan Turning is talking about the verifier
是指让人来验证（现在是拟人，那时是真人）
but the verifier that he means is a person that's verifying
论文中描述了
this paper described
人员检验代码所需的操作流程
the process that a human being should take to verify the correctness of code
这与当今安全研究的不同点很有趣
which is a very interesting difference to how cybersecurity research is done nowadays
因为现在安全研究的论文，比如我们实验室的论文
because all of our papers when we do cybersecurity research for example in my lab
都在讨论一个自动化系统是如何分析代码找到漏洞的
discuss how an automated system would analyze code and check it for vulnerabilities
我们继续
let's roll on
在本模块中，我们将介绍两个主要的分析方法
in this module we'll cover two main analysis
静态分析和动态分析
static analysis and dynamic analysis
区别在于
the difference is
实际这是个哲学辩题
actually this is a philosophical debate
这些都是模糊的定义
these are muddy philosophical definition
有的静态分析技术会执行某些代码
there are static techniques that execute some code
有的动态分析技术不执行某些代码
there are dynamic techniques that don't execute some code
但区别在于
but the difference is
你的分析方法所执行或不执行的代码
does your analysis technique execute code or does it not execute code
是不是你要分析的代码
specifically execute the code that you're trying to analyze
这两种技术各有利弊
there are pros and cons to both techniques
我先把这张幻灯片修好，马上回来
let me fix this slide I'll be right back
两种技术各有利弊
there are pros and cons to both techniques
静态分析的优点是不需要执行目标程序
the pro to static analysis is that you don't need to execute the program
这真是太好了
this is humongously good
有些程序很难执行
some programs are incredibly hard to get to execute
等说到动态分析的时候我会举例子
I'll talk about that one when I mention dynamic analysis
静态分析的另一个优点是
another pro of static analysis
该技术是非常有根据的
actually these techniques are very founded
可以被数学证明有用
and very solid foundations that are mathematically proven to result in success
例如，静态分析可以保证
for example a static analysis could guarantee
能检测到所有类型的漏洞
the detection of all instances of a specific vulnerability
比如，静态分析对缓冲区溢出的识别
let's say static analysis that identifies buffer overflows
能保证检测到所有缓冲区溢出
could actually guarantee the detection of every single buffer overflow
问题是这也直接造成了它的一大缺点
the problem is this leads directly to the con
很不精准，误报多
is that they're incredibly imprecise and they rely on so much information
且需要在不执行程序的情况下从程序中提取很多信息
that they need to extract from the program itself without executing it
因为他们无法在执行时到处打听发生了什么
they can't actually like poke around at what's happening during execution
想象一下，如果你逆向时被要求不准使用gdb
imagine if you had to reverse engineer everything without GDB
那将十分痛苦
that would be a pain in the butt
它们需要源代码
they require source code even with
也不一定，有的分析二进制代码
not always there are static masters techniques on binary code
我们实验室正在研究这种
we are researching some of them in our research lab
但没有源代码中包含的信息，分析得很难受
but they suffer greatly without the information contained in source code
即使有源代码，它们也非常不精确
and even with source code they're incredibly imprecise
我的意思是
what I mean by this is consider I said
静态分析确实能保证成功检测到所有的bug
static analysis can guarantee successful detection of all bugs
不管他们是根据哪个标准认定的bug
that according to whatever specification they consider bugs to be
静态分析后
I can make a static analysis
它会告诉你，你程序的每条指令（夸张手法）
and I'll tell you that at every instruction in your program
都有缓冲区溢出
you will sugar a buffer overflow
严格来说，确实找到了程序中所有的缓冲区溢出
and technically I've just found all of your buffer overflows
但这种分析没太大用处
but that analysis is not very useful
静态分析能够保证发现缺陷
static analysis tend to be able to make guarantees that it will be able to find flaws
然而，它会发现很多所谓的误报
however it will find a lot of what is called false positives detections
将正常代码误认为有问题
that are not actually an issue
正因为如此
and because of this actually
静态分析的使用比您想象的要少得多
static analysis is much much less used than you might expect
另一边动态分析
right on the other side of the equation dynamic analysis
动态分析有它自己的优点
Dynamic analysis has its own pros
在程序运行时的动态分析
dynamic analysis  when you run the program
可能是在gdb中手动启动，或者在动态分析工具中自动启动
for example manually in GDB but automatically in dynamic analysis tools
优点是
the pros that typically
动态分析通常(并非总是)不需要源代码
dynamic analysis typically, not always, doesn't require source code
它能在程序运行时分析程序运行情况
it can actually run the program analyze what is going on etc
或者说有的强大的动态分析技术
or let's say rather there are powerful dynamic analysis techniques that
不需要源代码
do not require source code
动态分析是非常精确的
dynamic analysis is very precise
当它发现bug时
when it finds a bug
它能发现bug，是因为运行时触发了bug
it finds the bug because it has just triggered the bug
这意味着它能提供触发bug的输入数据，用于复现
that means it can give you an input data  that you can use to retrigger the bug
这不会把你的时间浪费在误报上
which means that dynamic analysis doesn't waste your time with false positives
检测到的bug都是真的
every detection is a true positive
相对的
on the other side of that
也只能发现触发到的代码的bug
you can only spot bugs if you have actually triggered that part of the code
这被称为假阴性（漏报）
this is called false negatives where
只要你不触发代码
if you just don't trigger code
动态分析系统将无法检测到那里的bug
the dynamic analysis system will fail to detect bugs there
它不会明说没bug
well it won't say there are no bugs
但它也不会说有bug
but it won't say that there are bugs
漏报
false negative
这就是所谓的代码覆盖问题
this is known as the dynamic coverage problem
为了对代码进行动态分析
in order to reason about code dynamically
你需要覆盖那段代码
you need to cover that code
我们将在本模块的另一个视频中讨论代码覆盖
we'll talk about code coverage in another video in this module
动态分析的另一个重要问题是
the other non-trivial issue that dynamic analysis has
要分析就必须要运行代码
is you have to run the code to analyze it
很明显，如果你在分析objdump或其他简单的东西
so obviously if you're analyzing objdump or something simple
那很简单，运行一下就行了
that's simple enough you just run it
但若是复杂的程序呢
but what about complex programs
若是那些需要复杂配置的程序呢
what about programs require complex configuration
库呢
what about libraries
如何动态分析libc库
how do you dynamically analyze libc
显然，你要能在不同程序触发libc中的代码
obviously you need to be able to trigger code inside libc through different programs
看看libc会做什么
to see what libc does
若是嵌入式设备呢
embedded devices
如果你有一份固件样例
if you have a firmware sample
就像Phineas Fisher对嵌入式设备做的那样
like Phineas Fisher did for some embedded device
如何使用动态分析来分析它呢
how do you use dynamic analysis to actually analyze it
这是一个尚未解决的问题
that is a very much an unsolved problem
这导致一个问题是
and as a result one problem is that
通常情况下，动态分析无法发现bug
often times you can't find bugs with dynamic analysis
当然，动态分析是
now of course dynamic analysis is of course
也许对我来说很明显，但对你来说还不是
obvious to me perhaps but not yet to you
动态分析是当今人类自动化漏洞挖掘技术的王道
dynamic analysis is king in the current state of human technology
我们将在整个模块中讨论它
as we'll talk about throughout the module
我们（整个社会）用动态分析技术找到了大量bug
we are as a society able to find quite a lot of bugs using dynamic techniques currently
静态分析技术还在追赶中
and static techniques are kind of catching up
这个情况不是不变的
this wasn't always the case
但就目前来说是这样
but it's currently the case right now
在这个模块中要记住
keep in mind throughout this module
Michael Zalewski
我们将在之后几集讨论他是谁
and we'll talk about who he is a couple of videos from now
Michael Zalewski有一句名言
Michael Zalewski  has this famous quote
目前的程序分析技术才刚刚起步
that all of this program analysis stuff right now is kind of just starting out
这句话是2015年的
this quote is from 2015.
五年后，情况依然如此
five years later it is still the case that
使用符号执行、协执行、静态分析等新兴技术
the uses of symbolic execution concolic execution static analysis and other emerging technologies
来发现复杂的、非结构化的和无注释的，代码中的漏洞
to spot substantial vulnerabilities in complex unstructured and non annotated code
尚处于萌芽阶段
are still in their infancy
这很难
this is hard
本模块旨在让你了解早期阶段的各种可能性
this module is designed to give you a glimpse at these early stages at what is possible
也许能激励你
and maybe inspire you
加入正在进行的研究
to jump in on the research being done
让这一切成为现实
to try to make this a reality
各地都在进行这项研究
this research is being done all over the place
包括亚利桑那州立大学中我和我优秀同事们的实验室
including at Arizona State University in my lab along with my awesome colleagues
如果你对这样的研究感兴趣
if you are interested in doing such research
并看到了这里
and you made it this far in the course
给我发邮件，我们详谈
shoot me an email and we'll talk
我们在接下来的视频中再见
otherwise I'll see you in the rest of the videos